Donald Trump and Vladimir Putin have shaken up the world of international politics.
And all in just one week. First Trump and Putin had a
phone call in which they pledged to find a solution to the war in Ukraine,
just when three years have passed since the Russian invasion.
Later came the Munich Security Conference, where one thing became clear: Europe and
The United States maintains important differences on multiple international issues,
and especially the war in Ukraine. Although it all came together with this image.
Washington and Moscow foreign ministers meeting in Saudi Arabia, something that did not
has been happening since the invasion of Ukraine began. The result: a diplomatic earthquake because
All these Europe and Ukraine have not participated in the negotiations… And, as if that were not enough,
Trump even called Ukrainian President Volodymyr Zelensky a “dictator.”
Many are now asking, are we facing a new world order? Here we review what has happened.
in a week that may be one of the most crucial since the start of the war in Ukraine.
It all started on February 12, when Trump and Putin spoke on the phone.
A dramatic turnaround: it was the first direct contact between the leaders of the United States
and Russia since the war in Ukraine began. They agreed to immediately begin negotiations.
to end the war in Ukraine. And Trump assured that they will work to stop,
I open quotes, “the millions of deaths that are occurring in the war.”
The exact number of victims is unknown, but the BBC Russian Service estimated, from
estimates that some 148,000 Ukrainian and Russian soldiers have died in almost 3 years of war.
Immediately afterward, Trump held another conversation, this time with Ukrainian President Zelensky.
He described the talk as very good and said that both Zelensky and Putin are seeking peace,
although he assured that it would not be "practical" for Ukraine to be a member of NATO. And this is
One of Zelensky's big goals. And that same day, Kyiv received another hard
coup. US Secretary of Defense Pete Hegseth,
He said it was “unrealistic” for Ukraine to want to return to the borders it had before 2014.
Many interpreted these statements as a turn by Washington in favor of the
Russia's territorial aspirations. And this rapprochement between Washington
and Moscow, in turn, showed the fracture between its traditional European allies and the United States,
its main partner in NATO. In addition to the differences in their
positions European countries and Ukraine were excluded from the negotiations
This rupture became evident at the Munich Security Conference,
the largest independent forum on defense, which took place between February 14 and 16.
Here, the protagonist was the Vice President of the United States,
JD Vance. He did not mention the war in Ukraine in his speech, but instead focused on accusing
European leaders for censoring freedom of expression and failing to control immigration.
He also met with Zelensky, although they did not announce any agreement.
The exclusion of Europe and Ukraine triggered the following event.
On the 17th, French President Emmanuel Macron convened an informal summit with the
leaders of the main European countries to coordinate a common strategy.
Although the meeting also made clear the internal divisions in Europe. For example,
The United Kingdom proposed deploying peacekeepers in Ukraine, something that other countries rejected,
like Germany or Spain. And, of course, from
Ukraine also expressed its dismay at not participating in these talks.
But the event that finally shook the diplomatic board occurred on the day
18 in Riyadh, the capital of Saudi Arabia. Delegations from the United States and Russia
gathered there to begin talks on how to end the war in Ukraine and
to normalize bilateral relations. A crucial meeting, since they had not met
gathered since the Russian invasion in February 2022.
It was attended by US Secretary of State Marco Rubio and Minister
Russian Foreign Minister Sergei Lavrov. They agreed to begin negotiations to
achieve a "lasting and stable" peace. And they pledged to
mutually reinstate their ambassadors. However, this move was seen in
Europe as an alignment of the United States with Russian interests.
And for some analysts, such as Sarah Rainsford, BBC correspondent in Eastern Europe,
The image of this meeting is “exactly what Moscow wants.”
As a result, the relationship between Ukraine and the United States,
which has been Kiev's closest ally in the war with Russia so far, has been broken.
Trump and Zelensky have exchanged harsh messages in recent days.
First Trump accused Ukraine, without evidence, of starting the war, which it did in fact start.
with the Russian invasion and the failure to negotiate a solution in the last three and a half years.
He also stated that Zelensky has a 4% approval rating. However,
A recent poll in December gave him 52% popular confidence.
And he criticized the fact that no elections were held in Ukraine,
something that has not happened since the country is under martial law due to the war.
Zelensky responded by accusing Trump of being swayed by disinformation created by Russia.
And Trump reacted harshly.
Furthermore, the two leaders disagreed over Washington's support for Kyiv during the war.
And Zelensky assured that the United States wants the equivalent of 500 billion dollars.
in rare minerals from Ukraine in exchange for their continued support.
According to experts, it is feared that all these disagreements will give Putin confidence to
escalate its military actions in Eastern Europe. And that the US rhetoric on Ukraine
It now surprisingly coincides with that of Russia and diverges from that of Europe, NATO and Ukraine.